Matt Greensmith

Operations Engineer

matt@mattgreensmith.net (503) 592-0020 mattgreensmith.net github.com/mgreensmith www.linkedin.com/in/mattgreensmith

Summary

Operations engineer / linux systems administrator / infrastructure developer with experience in a broad range of current and emergent technologies. Focusing on web stack operations especially Ruby on Rails, infrastructure in code, configuration management with chef and puppet, software development in ruby, monitoring and alerting, virtualized and cloud platforms. Experienced builder and operator of high-volume high-availability web application stacks.

Skills

Web Ops Stack	Ruby on Rails, apache, nginx, unicorn, passenger, thin, resque, tomcat, solr. MySQL, PostgreSQL and redis. Nagios, cacti, runit, monit, munin, collectd, statsd, graphite, TeamCity, Jenkins.
Programming	Infrastructure as code with Chef and Puppet. Prefer Ruby and shell, OK in perl, python. Web apps with Sinatra, limited Rails. Expert git.
Infrastructure Services	BIND, dhcp, NFS, samba, rsyslog, OpenSSH, backupPC, bacula, postfix, MailScanner, mailman, LTSP, LDAP, pxe, cobbler.
Virtualization	VMWare vSphere 4 and vSphere5, VMWare Fusion, VirtualBox, Vagrant, some Parallels, KVM, lxc.
Storage	Nexentastor SAN with SAS multipathing and HA clustering, iSCSI, NFS, Synology NAS appliances, familiar with NetApp, OpenFiler and FreeNAS.
Networking	pfSense, PaloAlto, Vyatta, F5. VLANs, link aggregation, network troubleshooting at all layers.
Hardware	White box server builds from component level, server racking and (painstakingly tidy) cabling. Dell, Lenovo, Apple hardware repairs.
SaaS Products	Rackspace Cloud, Amazon S3 and Cloudfront, GitHub, New Relic, PagerDuty, Zendesk, Confluence and Jira, Pivotal Tracker, Exceptional.io, Google Apps administration.

Professional Experience

Operations Engineer

November 2012 - Present

Analog Analytics

Role includes Linux administration, infrastructure development and integration with chef, SME and primary operational support for multiple high-volume ruby on rails applications. Work closely with developers, project management and support teams in an open and collaborative DevOps-focused workplace. Operate and maintain multiple application stacks running in a hybrid cloud-and-physical-machine hosted environment.

- Collaboratively architected and built out a multi-site hosting infrastructure for a high-profile multi-million-dollar social commerce platform. Successfully launched the site and have operated since May with no unscheduled downtime in production.
- Developed automated deployment toolchain, leveraging chef to create a pushbutton code validation and deploy process triggered from a Sinatra-backed web interface. This enabled us to transfer responsibility for code deployments from the DevOps team to the project management team.
- Migrated service supervisor for key web services from bluepill to runit to improve reliability and enable zero-downtime code deploys.

Renewable Funding, LLC.

Excelled in a multifaceted role that included site operations support and reliability engineering, infrastructure administration, desktop and user support at all levels. Reporting to the Data and Systems Engineering Manager, I was the only other IT/Ops employee in this small startup company.

- Responsible development and operation of a highly-automated web stack serving production Rails applications for multiple corporate and government clients. Worked closely with development team to maximize site availability and reliability.
- Improved monitoring capability by deploying munin to all servers, including development of a custom web service to allow client nodes to self-register with the munin server in an automated fashion.
- Managed and participated in numerous infrastructure projects. Designed and build automated Windows imaging and configuration management workflow based on MDT and ManageEngine. Collaboratively planned and executed a full directory service migration from Apple Open Directory to MS Active Directory.

Technology Support Specialist (Systems Administrator)

2008 - 2012

Newberg School District

Key member of a small team of IT generalists tasked with designing, building, maintaining and supporting all district IT assets. Systems administration of 50+ physical and virtual servers in multiple data centers. Helpdesk for 600 staff and 6000 K-12 student users, and desktop support for 2500+ workstations across 11 sites.

- Improved data storage availability and efficiency by implementing SAN-based storage. Designed, built and installed a multi-node, highly-available Nexentastor-based SAN. Configured iSCSI and NFS services, tiered backups and HA failover.
- Reduced data center power consumption, improved server efficiency and reliability by virtualizing servers. Specified, built and configured a VMWare vSphere 4 cluster with SAN-based multipath iSCSI storage. Later upgraded all hosts to vSphere 5.
- Improved remote administration capability for Mac workstations by developing a web-based login hook repository from which workstations would automatically obtain updated login scripts. Client-side scripts written in bash.
- Developed web-based administration console for Linux servers using Perl and Javascript. This reduced IT staff workload by allowing non-technical users to perform common administrative tasks without requiring shell access to servers.
- Designed and implemented network monitoring system based on Nagios (Opsview) and Cacti to monitor 1000+ services across hundreds of devices. This significantly improved department visibility of network status and decreased response and resolution times for outages.

IT Consultant 2008

Robert Half Technology

Provided IT technician services under contract to multiple clients, including:

- A Major National Bank: Deployment and installation of new POS hardware and software, large-scale infrastructure uplift.
- A Software Development Company: Workstation and hardware support.
- Newberg School District: IT helpdesk services for 600 staff and 6000 students, as well as systems administration tasks.

Employee Performance Supervisor

2003 - 2005

NuComm International

Managed teams of 20-40 technical support representatives with proven ability to drive agent performance, impart technical knowledge, and exceed all client and internal targets for productivity and customer satisfaction. Excellence in this role led to numerous special projects involving supervisor training, operations management, reporting and analysis.

Telephone Service Representative

2002 - 2003

NuComm International

Excelled at business-to-consumer tier I and tier II technical support, surpassed all productivity targets, exceeded 90% issue resolution rate. Supported end-user OS and hardware configuration for LAN/WAN connectivity, email, personal web hosting. Utilized Remedy issue tracking software, remote desktop, SNMP tools, ACSR, ICOMs.

Education

CPL(H), Commercial Pilot - Helicopter

2007 - 2008

Hillsboro Aviation

Obtained FAA Commercial Pilot License with Helicopter Endorsement.

Bachelor of Applied Information Science (Incomplete)

2005 - 2006

Sheridan College

Achieved 3.88 GPA during three semesters of coursework towards a Bachelor of Applied Information Science – Information Systems Security.

Certifications

CompTIA A+	2008
CompTIA Network+	2011
Microsoft Certified Professional (MCP)	2011

Additional

Canadian citizen, US permanent resident with full employment authorization (green card).

Mentor of the Newberg High School FIRST Robotics team.